[SPEAKER_06]: So, who can tell me what is samādhi?
[SPEAKER_03]: Establishment of the mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: Can you describe that?
[SPEAKER_06]: What is establishment of the mind?
[SPEAKER_03]: Seeing the sign of the mind is one way to describe it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, eh... any description will be a thought or an image.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, it's always... the mind always proceeds.
[SPEAKER_06]: Any description that you can give... Yeah, but still... Somebody comes to the Buddha and wants to learn what is samādhi.
[SPEAKER_06]: You can just stick to samādhi.
[SPEAKER_06]: You don't have to describe the mind and the sign and what's behind.
[SPEAKER_06]: Just, what is samādhi?
[SPEAKER_06]: I mean, we translate it as composure.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, can you describe what is composure to somebody that doesn't really know what to look for?
[SPEAKER_06]: So, give me just practical, even mundane examples of what is composure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Instead of getting drawn into the content of thoughts or images, one sees those
[SPEAKER_03]: Thoughts or images as thoughts.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, one becomes established on the nature of one's experience.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: But before we get talking about that level, can anybody give me a mundane example of composure?
[SPEAKER_06]: Because people do experience, say somebody who doesn't practice the dhamma, would experience throughout their life forms of composure.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, what is that composure?
[SPEAKER_06]: Just give me some examples of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not being bothered or moved or disturbed by disturbing events, let's say, or particular circumstances that arise, you cannot be shaken by them.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, like, for example, if somebody is in a good mood, for whatever reason,
[SPEAKER_06]: They go throughout the day in a good mood and even bad things or bad people don't necessarily affect them.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, it's not... the reason why I'm coming on to this is because it's not just the composure of an idea.
[SPEAKER_06]: It also... well, it is partially.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: But that idea implies emotional composure as a background of it.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, yeah, mood would be an example.
[SPEAKER_06]: Equally, someone's mind can be composed upon a not-so-good mood, which means even good things would annoy them and irritate them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they're kind of... anything that happens comes within that sort of bad mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, everything is... has a kind of a disagreeable baseline, I suppose, or an agreeable baseline, if they're in a good mood.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, composure then.
[SPEAKER_06]: Does a person have a say in their mood?
[SPEAKER_06]: No?
[SPEAKER_06]: No.
[SPEAKER_06]: Really?
[SPEAKER_01]: I would say yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, if you say no, why is it no?
[SPEAKER_00]: I think there's no personal... you can't change it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It presents it of its own.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, that's true on that level.
[SPEAKER_06]: And if you say yes, why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it is possible, like even in mundane terms, like my father would say, no, I can put myself in a good mood by thinking about certain things, reminding myself of how
[SPEAKER_01]: I suppose fortunate I am compared to other people, so, you know, I can keep my mood not from going too bad or too good by doing certain things and by reflecting in certain ways.
[SPEAKER_06]: And actually, yeah, both are right.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, what you were referring to is the aspect of, yeah, mind is on its own.
[SPEAKER_06]: Moods of the mind are phenomenon on its own.
[SPEAKER_06]: However, your actions, as in, are you allowing the unrestrained wild animal mind to go where it wants?
[SPEAKER_06]: Moods will get worse.
[SPEAKER_06]: Moods will get depressed.
[SPEAKER_06]: Moods will get, like, agitated, or along those lines.
[SPEAKER_06]: Or are you making the effort to restrain it?
[SPEAKER_06]: Moods will get lighter and better.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, you don't have a say in the phenomenon of the mood, but you do actually have a say whether you're indirectly feeding it or not.
[SPEAKER_06]: And that's that recognition.
[SPEAKER_06]: And exactly like, you know, as the Buddha said, the one who doesn't live a celibate life, a householder in the suttas, if he frequently recollects the Buddha, the dhamma, the saṅgha, the virtue, he will get pleasant abiding of a type of samādhi here and now.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, the mind will be composed upon this frequent reflection upon certain values.
[SPEAKER_06]: Even when you don't feel like thinking about those things, you make the effort to think about those things and make a practice out of reflecting upon those things day in, day out.
[SPEAKER_06]: And those effectual composures of the mind, as the Buddha said, are pleasant abiding for the level of somebody who is not a celibate.
[SPEAKER_06]: Now, of course, if you want to have higher pleasant abidings, you need to restrain more, but the point is, it comes down to that frequent recollection and reflection.
[SPEAKER_06]: That is what will incline the mind.
[SPEAKER_06]: And what I said, what one frequently thinks and ponders on, that's where the mind is going to go.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, is it sensuality or non-sensuality?
[SPEAKER_06]: Is it irritation, fault-finding, ill-will or non-irritation, not fault-finding, not ill-will?
[SPEAKER_06]: And that's that background practice, that reflection.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, how is then composure, frequent recollection, different from concentration?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, concentration, do you mean in terms of, like, focusing practices?
[SPEAKER_06]: I mean concentration.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, let's say, what is concentration, in the most mundane terms?
[SPEAKER_06]: How would you describe concentration?
[SPEAKER_06]: Somebody says, hey, what's concentration?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, yeah, it is a kind of... you're... at the expense of everything else, you're honing in on something particular.
[SPEAKER_06]: Aha.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, if I don't have any experience in anything, and I come and ask you, I heard this word concentration.
[SPEAKER_06]: How do I do that?
[SPEAKER_05]: What is concentration?
[SPEAKER_06]: So, how would you just advise me, in most mundane terms?
[SPEAKER_06]: Just pick an object and focus on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It could be as mundane as like... Yeah, just mundane examples of concentration.
[SPEAKER_01]: Trying to play the piano, being very focused on having something that is totally absorbing all of your attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the sense of, I have to focus on this thing, and if I forget it for a second, I'm going to make a mistake in my piano playing, so I can't do that.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, it comes down to attention, to detail, to a particular thing that's in front of you.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, how is that, or is that, attention to a particular object of your senses, or even idea, for that matter?
[SPEAKER_06]: Is that different from recollection that we just talked about?
[SPEAKER_06]: The composure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: How?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it depends upon that object.
[SPEAKER_01]: What?
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, what?
[SPEAKER_01]: It depends on that object that your mind is focused on.
[SPEAKER_06]: What depends on the object?
[SPEAKER_06]: Concentration.
[SPEAKER_01]: Concentration.
[SPEAKER_06]: How?
[SPEAKER_06]: Where is the dependence?
[SPEAKER_06]: Because you could say, I don't care what I'm concentrated on, I practice concentration of everything, anything that comes into my field of attention, I attend to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, okay, I see what you mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: It depends on that object basically staying the same and not going away, because if you're sort of...
[SPEAKER_01]: I concentrate on anything that comes into my field of attention, then you wouldn't call that really concentration, because it would be diverse, like it would be any type of object that...
[SPEAKER_06]: But that's my point.
[SPEAKER_06]: Does it matter what object it is in order to define a concentration?
[SPEAKER_06]: So, it's what you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's how you...
[SPEAKER_06]: So, then you could concentrate on any different object that come your way and still practice concentration, even if they're different objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, then...
[SPEAKER_06]: So, how's that different?
[SPEAKER_06]: Or is that different?
[SPEAKER_06]: Or why is that different?
[SPEAKER_06]: Because, like, if we say recollecting the certain themes,
[SPEAKER_06]: Can you concentrate on them?
[SPEAKER_06]: Is that what we are saying?
[SPEAKER_06]: Can that be there?
[SPEAKER_06]: So, what's the difference then, if you're concentrating?
[SPEAKER_05]: That one is concentrating, one is attending a thing, whereas recollection...
[SPEAKER_05]: As I understand, it's more about discerning, so to say, or seeing the background, but seeing...
[SPEAKER_06]: In like mundane terms, you could say one of the most obvious differences is when you're concentrating, you are doing it.
[SPEAKER_06]: You are attending what's there.
[SPEAKER_06]: But when you're recollecting, there is already a certain degree
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, it's indirect.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, you set up, as Buddha said, you know, like...
[SPEAKER_06]: The water comes down the mountain and it starts filling the pools.
[SPEAKER_06]: And so, imagine now, you're just... you can't stop that water.
[SPEAKER_06]: Or you can't...
[SPEAKER_06]: I mean, you can try, but the point is to direct it elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_06]: By setting this context, they will then encourage you to go in that direction.
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh, yeah, don't look there.
[SPEAKER_06]: Look here.
[SPEAKER_06]: Look at this.
[SPEAKER_06]: And it's bad over there.
[SPEAKER_06]: And all this danger, peril, lack of satisfaction, and so on, are the themes that, if you sustain, the mind will turn away from it.
[SPEAKER_06]: And why can't you do that with concentration?
[SPEAKER_06]: Why can't you just concentrate on your mind and make it go that way?
[SPEAKER_05]: Because it's not an object that you can attend.
[SPEAKER_06]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_06]: People keep thinking that concentration is the mind watching.
[SPEAKER_06]: You don't see your mind when you're concentrated with it.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's not a sense object.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's always before.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, in the same sense, I will
[SPEAKER_06]: It's actually exactly the same.
[SPEAKER_06]: If I were to be looking at visual things to see my eyes there, that is impossible.
[SPEAKER_06]: Or feeling tactile sensations to see my body there, that is impossible.
[SPEAKER_06]: Body is the background, body is the organ for your sensations.
[SPEAKER_06]: So then, can concentration be useful?
[SPEAKER_05]: In terms of practice?
[SPEAKER_03]: Initially, I mean, it's a prerequisite for reading the suttas, getting information, getting data, in terms of... Well, attending to right things, sure.
[SPEAKER_06]: But I'm talking about practice of concentration in itself.
[SPEAKER_06]: Can that be beneficial?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes, if the mind is inclining towards unwholesome things, it could be helpful to intentionally direct it towards more wholesome things.
[SPEAKER_04]: But can you discern wholesome when you're concentrated?
[SPEAKER_04]: Is that a possibility?
[SPEAKER_05]: I mean, some things are obviously unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, yes, but while being concentrated, do you have the possibility of discerning whether you are attending to something wholesome or not?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not by virtue of the concentration.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or if you could, but it would be at the expense of the concentration.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: So then, the question comes down to recognizing that degree or clarifying it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Where does attention become concentration practice?
[SPEAKER_06]: Like, you cannot but not attend anything.
[SPEAKER_06]: But you can certainly learn how not to overlook the background, the context.
[SPEAKER_06]: The meaning, the intentionality behind whatever you're attending currently.
[SPEAKER_06]: And that context is what tells you.
[SPEAKER_06]: Because that's where your intentions are.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's what tells you whether this is wholesome, and I should allow it to be attended further, or unwholesome, and I should not welcome it, not delight it, and make sure I don't attend, as the Buddha said, particular signs and features that are inducive of lust and would increase the unwholesome state.
[SPEAKER_06]: But it doesn't say, I'll just focus on it harder, concentrate, because, see, even if even if it's a good thing,
[SPEAKER_06]: Say, if it's a wholesome thing, if you actually think, okay, if I double down now in attending to it, I'll get there faster.
[SPEAKER_06]: You want to distract yourself further.
[SPEAKER_06]: It always has to be done.
[SPEAKER_06]: It always has to be done at the expense of the context, at the expense of composure.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes, that's what I meant.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, ironically, the concentration practice is directly opposite of samādhi practice.
[SPEAKER_06]: Samādhi being the composure of the theme, of the context, recollecting things rightly, that then sustain and incline your mind in certain way.
[SPEAKER_06]: Concentration, basically, means overshooting the mark and abandoning the context.
[SPEAKER_06]: Even if it's, as I said, concentrating upon the good things.
[SPEAKER_06]: And that's why it's that the whole practice is to learn how not to overshoot or, like, undershoot, in a sense of ignore the whole thing, of course.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, attend to something, but don't let it become a focusing concentration object in practice, because you cannot possibly do that and at the same time sustain the background context of your intentionality, the meaning, the mood behind all of that.
[SPEAKER_06]: So then, can anybody elaborate or give some examples on, as we said, composure equals establishment of the mind, equals right recollections, right themes, right context, equals putting the work there.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, can anybody give me a few examples of right composure and right recollection?
[SPEAKER_06]: A few practices, let's say like that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Seeing the body as present, and seeing the body always present, whatever one is doing.
[SPEAKER_06]: How would you see that?
[SPEAKER_06]: How would you go about it?
[SPEAKER_06]: So, you say, yeah, okay, I want to see the body present.
[SPEAKER_06]: What do I do?
[SPEAKER_05]: By not being too involved with what one is doing, at any time.
[SPEAKER_06]: What constitutes being too involved?
[SPEAKER_05]: What we just described, like concentrating on something, in a sense, and not...
[SPEAKER_06]: Right.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, abstaining from concentration...
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Would then that reveal me the background?
[SPEAKER_06]: Not in itself.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, back on to my original question then.
[SPEAKER_06]: How do I reveal that background?
[SPEAKER_06]: What do I do?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it could be just those basic things, like the suttas say, you know, being, um...
[SPEAKER_01]: Aware of what you're doing, not in the sense of the actual...
[SPEAKER_01]: Object of activity that you're doing, but what your body is doing, in the sense of, okay, I'm sitting, walking, getting up, but just as a way to kind of indirectly notice the fact that no matter where you do, what you're, where you're going, your body is always there.
[SPEAKER_06]: But how would I prevent that from becoming my concentration object?
[SPEAKER_01]: See, that often does come, like I was doing it like that, as in trying to make it an object of, okay, I am doing this, I am doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do I not do that?
[SPEAKER_06]: How do I establish my mind?
[SPEAKER_05]: How do I sustain and develop the right context, the right mood, so I won't fall into... Like you said earlier, to understand or... to understand that the body, the body that we are talking about now, cannot be seen as an object.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, how do you understand that?
[SPEAKER_06]: What do I do to get to that understanding?
[SPEAKER_06]: What would be the necessary?
[SPEAKER_00]: Frequently reflect and ponder upon it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: And in order to frequently reflect and ponder upon it, what do I need?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not forgetting the theme.
[SPEAKER_06]: Where do I get the theme from?
[SPEAKER_06]: Where do I get details about the theme?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, you learn about the themes that obviously counter your whole experience.
[SPEAKER_06]: You do want to.
[SPEAKER_06]: The whole tendency is to attend what's right in front of you.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, that's the definition of, like, essentiality in general.
[SPEAKER_06]: Like, living, your being existing on the level of sense objects.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's the measure of what's real.
[SPEAKER_06]: So then, whatever you attend to it, you make it an object by overly doing so.
[SPEAKER_06]: Ayoniso manasikāra, let's put it that way.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, then you learn about the right things, but you will still be making them objects of your attention.
[SPEAKER_06]: But if you study, if you hear, if you make sufficient effort to recollect and re-discern and re-clarify, you will be learning how not to.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, in other words, in order for you to have the right composure, right establishment of the mind, you need to abandon all of your wrong views that require certain degree of attention, certain degree of concentration, certain degrees of assumption of sense objects and so on.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, you need the right view.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, we're back on to what we always say.
[SPEAKER_06]: You can't get the right samādhi without the right view, because it's not a technique, it's not a method that will have automatic result if you go through certain steps.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's the right context, the right establishment, the right mood, the mood of a neutral feeling that's not perturbed by pleasant or unpleasant, by agreeable or disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, yeah, you learn the themes by studying the suttas and, again, it won't take that much of study to see that that's what Buddha was often talking about.
[SPEAKER_06]: Incline your mind towards wholesome.
[SPEAKER_06]: Take it away from unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_06]: How do you do it?
[SPEAKER_06]: Well, not by watching your belly movements or soles of your feet.
[SPEAKER_06]: You do it by pondering on the danger, the peril, the lack of satisfaction, the benefits, all these values that you actually have to keep sustaining through your own active thinking and reflection.
[SPEAKER_06]: And that's what the first jhāna becomes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Active thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_06]: That is fully
[SPEAKER_06]: Withdrawn, separated, went beyond the sensual domain.
[SPEAKER_06]: The domain where you assume the sense objects to be the measure of your being, of what is.
[SPEAKER_06]: And see, thinking and pondering clearly for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, you have to really work, make the effort, be prepared to make the effort to try and understand what the suttas are genuinely talking about, or what you might hear somebody saying that doesn't initially... it can't initially make perfect sense to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to be prepared to question your, sort of, assumptions of what these things mean.
[SPEAKER_03]: You start in this position of ignorance, in the sense when you start reading.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it's wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything is misunderstood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything is, like, or... and you, yeah... just...
[SPEAKER_01]: Just to kind of see that that type of attention is possible, or that there is another way of attending to things, that there is a kind of a background form of attention, or peripheral attention, or whatever you want to call it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever word you might say, initially, it won't make sense.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's just basically learning how to... how to attend.
[SPEAKER_06]: Because now, you start by over-attending everything.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Or completely not attending what you need.
[SPEAKER_06]: Just either ignoring or overdoing.
[SPEAKER_06]: The middle ground of it, where attention is there, without you losing the sight of its context, of its origin, of its womb, yoniso, that needs to be learned.
[SPEAKER_06]: That needs to be discerned first, sustained, endured, and then kind of recognized for what it is.
[SPEAKER_06]: And then, yes, you can you can cultivate.
[SPEAKER_06]: But even then, it won't become an object of your cultivation in that
[SPEAKER_06]: Concentration sense.
[SPEAKER_06]: In the broadest theoretical sense, yeah, it's phenomenal.
[SPEAKER_06]: It can be a theme, an object, that you think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an indirect way, not directly wanting to change what is in front of you, but changing...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's indirect way.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...changing the context, and that will automatically change...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, as I said, you kind of... you guide, you encourage your mind in certain... to go in certain directions.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like that simile of the irrigators...
[SPEAKER_01]: Directing the water.
[SPEAKER_01]: Directing the water, like you can't bring the water to that...
[SPEAKER_06]: But you know it will go, if you create the pathway for it.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, okay, so now that we clarified that you need to know, or you need to abandon the wrong views and wrong assumptions that revolve around the nature of your own current attention slash over-attention.
[SPEAKER_06]: What are the examples of some mind establishments upon the right contexts, the right composures?
[SPEAKER_06]: That would be like the most basic, basic example.
[SPEAKER_04]: The impermanence of phenomena.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, but as a mood that your mind is established upon, as an imperturbable mood, how would you... That would be more closely... Coming out of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, well, then you would go into anxiety or despair.
[SPEAKER_04]: This might be how impermanence reveals itself first.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that could also be seen as a mood.
[SPEAKER_04]: One can be in an anxious mood.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, yeah, of course, yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Which means then you become perturbed.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, how can you remain unperturbed when the point comes for you to think about impermanence, anxiety, cessation?
[SPEAKER_06]: How can the mind remain unperturbed?
[SPEAKER_05]: By restraining before us.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, does the restraint and virtue, does that require a certain context?
[SPEAKER_06]: A certain unifying idea?
[SPEAKER_05]: Not necessarily.
[SPEAKER_06]: How would you then know what to do?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes, I mean, at least from the beginning.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, no, I know.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm just adding to it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Even then, it's not that blind.
[SPEAKER_06]: Again, you wouldn't... you wouldn't even know what to do, unless there's some unifying idea of what restraint is.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, that is what defines your behavior, which you're referring to, is that then, in return,
[SPEAKER_06]: Practicing that behavior will then contribute further toward that thing.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, it can grow and develop simply through sense restraint and not breaking the precepts, not doing things that are contrary to the theme you took on.
[SPEAKER_06]: And that is already form of samādhi.
[SPEAKER_06]: And now you can... How do you... How do you increase?
[SPEAKER_06]: Let's say like that.
[SPEAKER_06]: How do you cultivate
[SPEAKER_06]: The samādhi of virtue, the samādhi of sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_06]: Is it by restraining even harder and saying no and creating even more rules?
[SPEAKER_06]: What is it then, if it's not that?
[SPEAKER_06]: How would you cultivate, bring to fulfillment the samādhi of virtue?
[SPEAKER_06]: If you're not creating more rules and adding more observances to do.
[SPEAKER_06]: Clarifying the danger of craving.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, by frequently thinking about, while you're still doing the same restraint and same virtue, you're not adding more things to say no to.
[SPEAKER_06]: But that doesn't mean, oh, okay, so I'm virtuous now, I can stop thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, actually.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes, you're virtuous.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes, you're sensuously trained.
[SPEAKER_06]: And now, often, think about the danger of non-virtue, the peril of sensuality, the peril of acting out of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_06]: And that's how you're cultivating it further.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, you don't need to do externally anything more, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: The benefits of that virtue.
[SPEAKER_02]: The benefits of virtue.
[SPEAKER_02]: The joy that comes from it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: The joy that you factually know comes from it.
[SPEAKER_06]: When you're blameless, when virtue is unbroken.
[SPEAKER_04]: That might also take some time, though, in terms of the virtue.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, some good reasons or some faith or confidence in the beginning might also be a unifying factor for sticking to the virtue.
[SPEAKER_06]: Exactly, yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's why, basically, all of those powers that the Buddha talks about,
[SPEAKER_06]: In the suttas, they're all kind of exactly that, unifying factors.
[SPEAKER_06]: There are certain things that enable you to then cultivate the right context and right practice, really, towards this passion.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, the point is that you realize that, okay, so, you keep the virtue, you're sense-restrained, and now you want to, even a householder in the suttas,
[SPEAKER_06]: Who keeps the five precepts, you know, but it's moderate, it's careful, watchful of his actions.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, he now wants to practice samādhi.
[SPEAKER_06]: And what did the Buddha then say?
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, then you sit, watch your nostrils, feel your belly coming up and down, sensations, move slowly, concentrate.
[SPEAKER_06]: No.
[SPEAKER_06]: He said what you do is then you recollect further.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, your samādhi practice is then on the level of actively thinking about certain themes, certain benefits, certain drawbacks, certain rewards, certain dangers, certain values, and the mind will become composed.
[SPEAKER_06]: As a result of that practice, that's obviously directly standing upon your virtue that is factually unbroken.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but experiencing the joy of that, recollecting your virtue and experiencing the joy of that, it does say the body becomes calm, you know, the mind becomes happy.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is, the composure leads to knowledge and vision.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, the point is that your body will become calm
[SPEAKER_06]: So, practice of samādhi, then, is practice of right pre-collection, right thinking, right evaluation,
[SPEAKER_06]: All of that results in samādhi.
[SPEAKER_06]: And then, a person who is factually... And by the way, I'm talking about a lay person now, like just five precepts.
[SPEAKER_06]: You don't even need to be celibate.
[SPEAKER_06]: But the rest of... Again, you set periods of day where you just sit and think about, actually, making your mind think about these themes and values.
[SPEAKER_06]: Not like, well, I keep the precepts so I can just do everything else within that and I don't need to think about it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes, yeah, you can go about it, but you won't have samādhi.
[SPEAKER_06]: You want the samādhi, you don't go to concentrate, you don't let your mind completely wild, you keep directing it and kind of re-enclosing it in that right context.
[SPEAKER_06]: And the factual result would be that if you spend, say, a few days building that up, it will start to persist in your mind.
[SPEAKER_06]: Those values, those themes, those thoughts, those states of mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let's say, something happens and then somebody says something to you and you get angry.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're like, oh, I'm not practicing Samādhi anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm getting angry.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then it's like, it's like, yeah, so then, in that instance, this idea, but I had this set, the idea that for three days I would reflect and think and ponder on this.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, in that instance, then, then,
[SPEAKER_03]: What is necessary is not to then impose some kind of, yeah, idea of me practicing samādhi in inverted commas, but to see
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, what has arisen by itself.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, you have no say in the fact that... Well, I think the first recognition should be simply that if you got angry, you didn't have samādhi to begin with.
[SPEAKER_02]: So... You got actively angry.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Well, no, I was gonna say that.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, if you establish... if you have actually been cultivating these themes and actively reflecting upon things the Buddha often say you should reflect upon,
[SPEAKER_06]: You wouldn't get as angry.
[SPEAKER_06]: And you would see that difference now.
[SPEAKER_06]: Because, see, the mind went really quite some distance in a good direction.
[SPEAKER_06]: And it's there.
[SPEAKER_06]: And somebody from a bad direction comes and tries to entice it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes, he might make it turn around and maybe start walking.
[SPEAKER_06]: But it's still quite far before it's actually in the bad field.
[SPEAKER_06]: And you will see that.
[SPEAKER_06]: So now, you will actually have confidence and recognize, okay, so I don't need to, you know, jump and choke that animal when it gets in and fight it directly.
[SPEAKER_06]: No, okay, now I got a bit distracted.
[SPEAKER_06]: Let me ignore this thing that's trying to take my attention through sensuality or anger and instead keep cultivating the same indirect
[SPEAKER_06]: So, if you have spent a few days thinking about it and something made you angry, and yes, you got really angry, the animal means, okay, I need to spend more time cultivating the same stuff.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, you see... And each time you cultivate it further, through right reflection, right recollection, right evaluation, and constantly think about those values and re-evaluating and so on, the mind is traveling in a good direction further and further and further.
[SPEAKER_06]: As long, of course, as your virtue remains unbroken and sense restraint protected.
[SPEAKER_06]: You kind of see that you were mistaken in a way, like... Yeah, you have to resist the urge to deal with it head on, because that would require abandoning the context and absorbing yourself in it to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_06]: The content, yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, that's why I keep saying before, most of meditation practice that people do today is rooted in aversion.
[SPEAKER_06]: Trying to get rid of the stuff that bothers them.
[SPEAKER_06]: Antidoting this with that, with this, with that, with it.
[SPEAKER_06]: No.
[SPEAKER_06]: All of that requires you to abandon the context or not even have it to begin with.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, that's how you then protect.
[SPEAKER_06]: Your samādhi.
[SPEAKER_06]: Again, for the lack of a better description, you protect it by recognizing where the importance is.
[SPEAKER_06]: Ah, it's on the level of value, value, re-value.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thinking about the danger and the peril of losing those values, because how quickly the mind will then go back into, you know, states that are not pleasant for me.
[SPEAKER_06]: Remembering all the joy, the lightness, the clarity you got as a result of established mood properly, where things that exactly used to make you furious or lustful haven't moved you now.
[SPEAKER_06]: Now, if you forget about your mind, it will start going back.
[SPEAKER_06]: Unless, of course, it's fully... has fully uprooted those kilesas, but...
[SPEAKER_06]: So, you realize, okay, so I don't need to fight things directly.
[SPEAKER_06]: All I need to do is virtue, sense restraint, obviously solitude to that degree, and then make a practice, active practice, of thinking and reflecting and re-evaluating these wholesome themes.
[SPEAKER_06]: And when they become dry, my mind starts getting distracted, that's where my work is.
[SPEAKER_06]: Not in finding something new to concentrate and so on.
[SPEAKER_06]: No, it's just finding ways to rekindle the same themes until the mind has traveled far enough that it cannot come back to these unwholesome pastures.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's also quite different to be doing all of those things that protect the samādhi, out of the knowledge that you are protecting your samādhi, and that that is what you're doing it for, rather than kind of just doing them to do them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Out of that kind of knowledge, okay, I'm, yeah, protecting my composure, protecting my mind.
[SPEAKER_06]: You wouldn't be able to discern any of that unless you're already seeing the signs of your mind.
[SPEAKER_06]: Unless you're already seeing that kind of indirect relationship between you and your own mind.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's not something you can directly attend to, have, possess, control.
[SPEAKER_06]: So you recognize it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, so it's basically like...
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, an animal that if you provide, open the gates, it will go there.
[SPEAKER_06]: If you close those gates and start encouraging, taking it away, sending it in the other way, it will go that way.
[SPEAKER_06]: So it will incline to whatever you're frequently thinking and pondering about, as the suttas say.
[SPEAKER_06]: So that's your job, to incline it in the right direction.
[SPEAKER_06]: Not to force it and, you know, shove the right direction down its throat.
[SPEAKER_06]: And all these themes and reflections and re-evaluations, can you do them by concentrating on them?
[SPEAKER_06]: No.
[SPEAKER_06]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_06]: But can you do them if you completely don't pay any attention to that theme?
[SPEAKER_06]: Equally impossible.
[SPEAKER_06]: So that's the middle ground I'm talking about.
[SPEAKER_06]: And factually, back on to the layperson who only keeps the five precepts, but recollects the dhamma, themes of the dhamma, the value of the virtue, all of those, and constantly is sort of feeding and sustaining those evaluations and re-evaluations in their mind.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, even within their lay setting, that is crowded and dusty, as the suttas often say, things that used to disturb them, or
[SPEAKER_06]: Disagreeable people and events will not be able to move their mind and make them lose perspective as much as they did before.
[SPEAKER_06]: And back on to the original example when we started.
[SPEAKER_06]: Imagine you're in a perpetually good mood.
[SPEAKER_06]: Now, you still recognize when a bad thing happens, but none of the things becomes bad enough to uproot your good mood, to uproot your imperturbable mood.
[SPEAKER_06]: Why?
[SPEAKER_06]: Because you have cultivated it, you have sustained it, you have protected it, and you have invested active effort in thinking, pondering, evaluating, re-evaluating about those things.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, in other words, you won't lose the context even when things are not good.
[SPEAKER_06]: As the suttas say, you know, if you cultivate the right context, establish the right composure,
[SPEAKER_06]: The body will become calm, joyful.
[SPEAKER_06]: The mind will become calm.
[SPEAKER_06]: Then, you can see and not act out of aversion.
[SPEAKER_06]: Even things that, as I said, are disagreeable, because you were calm beforehand, on that right level, where the mind has been withdrawn from unwholesome, then you won't be, by default, trying to get rid of the discomfort.
[SPEAKER_06]: In other words, you won't lose perspective.
[SPEAKER_06]: And then you will see it.
[SPEAKER_06]: And then you would see that, yes, exactly, if I were to engage with this and try to get rid of it, or if it's a agreeable thing, if I try to go for it, I will lose the comfort, I will lose the composure, thus I will lose the comfort of pleasant abiding here and now.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, and that's what the samādhi does in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes, calmness of the body, contentment of the mind.
[SPEAKER_06]: A happy mind is a contented mind.
[SPEAKER_06]: The one that's happy and contented can see things clearly, as the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_06]: But it clearly says before that as well, how do you get to that contented mind and happy mind and calm body and joyful body?
[SPEAKER_06]: Through basically developing these themes to the extent necessary.
[SPEAKER_06]: But see,
[SPEAKER_06]: People tend to ignore everything else in between and try to get a method that will calm the body, make the mind happy, get them to see the reality.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because they recognize that what they're trying to skip, so to say, is where the work is.
[SPEAKER_06]: I don't think they recognize.
[SPEAKER_06]: I think it's it's more like rooted in just not knowing where the problem is, which is in you already being on the level of sense objects through overly attending everything.
[SPEAKER_06]: And that's the measure.
[SPEAKER_06]: So now you hear about a practice and you think the practice is there.
[SPEAKER_06]: Concentrate on the right things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can even... what I was gonna say is like what's interesting, I think, yeah, I remember times before when, through kind of
[SPEAKER_01]: Actually, sort of, accidentally, in a way, or incidentally, doing some of the right things, I would sort of come to a relative degree of composure, let's say, to some extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I wouldn't have recognized
[SPEAKER_06]: That is something to protect and cultivate further.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: I wouldn't have recognized that as something to protect, nor would I have seen on what base it was, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: I would have kind of still thought that the important thing was some form of content, concentration.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by kind of not recognizing that,
[SPEAKER_01]: Where the... on what base this code of degree of composure was, I would just kind of... yeah, it would have stayed for a while and then become lost or... yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Because you haven't actually... recognized... back then, you haven't seen the mind for what it is.
[SPEAKER_06]: So you overlooked it.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's there.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's not like it doesn't exist in people that don't see it.
[SPEAKER_06]: They just don't know where to look.
[SPEAKER_06]: They don't know to what degree
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, even if you are doing some of the right things, it's not recognizing what things are the right things and what things are the wrong things.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, and that's exactly the definition of the right view.
[SPEAKER_06]: Knowing important as important and unimportant as unimportant.
[SPEAKER_06]: Without the right view, you will be basically regarding unimportant things as essential and important, and important things such as, oh, that what you just described, not really recognizing the importance of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if anger has arisen, instead of seeing that as a result of me previously not reflecting enough, I see it because of this content, because someone said this or somebody... and therefore...
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, you blame it on things.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I'm not...
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm not seeing, like, my responsibility and... And also, by blaming it on things, you'll see that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_06]: But it's not, really.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's the symptom of the problem.
[SPEAKER_06]: What is the problem?
[SPEAKER_06]: The problem is that the mind has not been established enough, properly.
[SPEAKER_06]: That will motivate me in future to...
[SPEAKER_06]: That's why I keep saying, like, you need to start recognizing that liability to anger or to lust is already... Oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, the fact that I'm liable, the fact that those things could arise, means the problem is still there.
[SPEAKER_06]: Means the mind is still liable to those things, which means mind has not been directed in the right context far enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I wouldn't have necessarily thought that, oh, if I was becoming angry, it's because of that person.
[SPEAKER_01]: I would have blamed myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I didn't let go of the anger fast enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: I wasn't concentrated hard enough.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: The moment in between my concentration slipped me.
[SPEAKER_06]: Next time I'll try harder.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: No, that's exactly.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's what most people, like again, most of them,
[SPEAKER_06]: The vast majority has genuine intention in practice, but as I said, there's been so much since the suttas, since the Buddha's passing away, that today's work is actually on the level of uncovering most of the stuff that's been covered with wrong instructions and wrong ideas.
[SPEAKER_06]: Not because somebody intentionally planned them.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's just that's, again, if your baseline is to over-attend things, not know what yoniso is, not understand means,
[SPEAKER_06]: Even when you attend to dhamma, you'll do so wrongly.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, people genuinely think that, oh, I need to practice concentration and absorb myself in moment to moment and not have anything slip my attention, so that then, disturbing things will not disturb them.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, I get disturbed when I have an oversight, basically, when I slip, when I forget about what I was supposed to look.
[SPEAKER_06]: But that's not what the suttas say.
[SPEAKER_06]: You get disturbed when there is greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_06]: Are greed, aversion, delusion on the level of objects of your senses and concentrations and sensations?
[SPEAKER_06]: No.
[SPEAKER_06]: They're on the level of your intention, on the level of your state of mind, on the level of your desires and themes and preconceived notions.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, that's where you need to uproot them.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, that's where all this directing the mind.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Indirectly, directly, the mind.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Like, basically, building, like, certain encouragements that will make the mind sort of go there.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's why one has to recognize, as you said, signs of the mind and the moods.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: And the patterns of thought.
[SPEAKER_06]: Recognizing the signs of the mind, it's basically this recognizing that the mind is not something that can be an object of your attention.
[SPEAKER_06]: It doesn't matter how hard you focus to the milliseconds of your experience, mind is not there.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's in the opposite direction.
[SPEAKER_06]: And then, recognizing that the way to deal with the mind, with such mind, with the mind of such nature, that cannot be directly accessed or attended,
[SPEAKER_06]: Well, first to refrain from trying to directly access and attend it, and then recognize that your work is on the level of building a wider context that your mind will have to be within.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, even... and you can start doing that even before you start seeing your mind.
[SPEAKER_06]: You know, you get the intellectual understanding, and then you start certain recollections, reflections, evaluations, dwelling on values, on benefits, on drawbacks, just day in, day out, just... and you might approach it through different themes, but you're doing the same recollection practice.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's on the basis of your virtue, sense, restraint and solitude.
[SPEAKER_06]: Your mind will then become visible.
[SPEAKER_06]: You will start seeing this background leaning towards this or towards that.
[SPEAKER_06]: And those are the signs and features of the mind.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's how you know the mind is there.
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh, footprints.
[SPEAKER_06]: He must have passed through here.
[SPEAKER_06]: And that's how you find it.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, the samādhi described here now, you could see how it's just part of the same development.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, because many people would recognize the value, because you can't deny, that's all the suttas talk about, the value of, you know, recollecting, re-evaluating, thinking, right themes, and frequently pondering upon, but then they would still think that the place for concentration is sort of... there is a place for concentration as a separate practice to this, that helps one another.
[SPEAKER_06]: It doesn't.
[SPEAKER_06]: You can only concentrate at the expense of a context.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, you want to practice samādhi.
[SPEAKER_06]: Samādhi, as the suttas say, is just composing and steadying down and fortifying your recollectedness, your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, your themes, your recollections, your frequently thinking and pondering, do that now, even more organized manner, like go under a root of a tree in a closed room and think and ponder even longer,
[SPEAKER_06]: Even more persistently, and that is your samādhi practice.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, it wouldn't be surprising then, that the result of that would be the first jhāna, which is defined by thinking and pondering, free from greed, aversion, delusion, free from hindrances.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, how do you free your thinking and pondering from the parasites of greed, aversion, delusion?
[SPEAKER_06]: Well, by thinking and pondering rightly, they will take it away.
[SPEAKER_06]: They will purify it like you purify the gold.
[SPEAKER_05]: By directing the mind away from this.
[SPEAKER_06]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_06]: By slowly taking it away and removing the impurities, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_05]: But I think as long as one does not recognize, as you described earlier, that there is this peripheral
[SPEAKER_06]: If there are these peripheral phenomena, so to say, then the latter would kind of make sense?
[SPEAKER_06]: Well, yes, because... Because there is nothing else.
[SPEAKER_05]: So what can I do, except... rather than catch every moment, so to say?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, you can learn, intellectually first, that catching the moment is taking you the wrong way.
[SPEAKER_06]: And recognize it for yourself.
[SPEAKER_06]: So you start refraining from it.
[SPEAKER_06]: And now that you know you're not supposed to be doing it, that's already a step forward.
[SPEAKER_06]: But yes, everything you do, from the baseline of where your attention is, which is over-attention, let's say like that, everything you do will be overly attended.
[SPEAKER_06]: Everything you do will be made an object of your attention.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's why the mind is invisible.
[SPEAKER_06]: But, if your views change, and you don't think you should be attending to things like that anymore, well, now you have a chance, actually, to discern the middle ground.
[SPEAKER_06]: But if your views don't change, then you're just going to be sort of creating a patchwork of trying to include everything that you find helpful and so on, you know, while at the same time ignoring the bigger picture, which is the fact that, well, the suttas don't talk about it, certainly not in the way commonly approached, and composure is the result of the right mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's the result of the right view.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, right view, right mindfulness, right intention, means right samādhi, right composure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because those are the things that you compose.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, but seven enlightenment factors apply to somebody who is at least Sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_06]: You need to have a right view for for any of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how would you describe, within this context, the practice, the practical way of guarding the sense doors?
[SPEAKER_06]: Same.
[SPEAKER_06]: Not losing the sight of where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, practically speaking, right here, right now, do you guard your eyes now by focusing on
[SPEAKER_06]: Lumps in your head and feeling sensations and abdomen.
[SPEAKER_06]: Or do you guard your eyes, not by thinking about your eyes, but by thinking about the peril of things that you shouldn't look at?
[SPEAKER_06]: Feeling that danger peripherally, not where your eyes are.
[SPEAKER_06]: Because, see, if I focus on my eyes, I'll do so at the expense of the context of what I shouldn't be looking at.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, you guard your sense doors by thinking rightly as to what you should
[SPEAKER_06]: Allow your eyes to look and what you shouldn't.
[SPEAKER_06]: And it is when you forget the danger of looking at the unwholesome things, that's when you intentionally choose to look.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's when you allow those wild animals of your eyes to go and look.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, you guard your eyes now.
[SPEAKER_06]: By basically being mindful of pretty much your situation as a whole, that in case something unsuitable for your eyes comes from some direction, you don't look at it, and if you look at it, you don't grasp pleasing signs and features.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, it's everywhere, but where the concentration of your eye is, or on your sights... sights, yeah, the objects of your eyes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Because you can't know, I'll just look down, I'll just look at this carpet, I'll just look at this carpet.
[SPEAKER_06]: Even that is defined by the actual context of why you're doing it.
[SPEAKER_06]: But do you think that just looking down here will make the problems go away?
[SPEAKER_06]: No.
[SPEAKER_06]: The risk of looking unwholesome, the risk of being infected by unwholesome, infected by lust, aversion and delusion, that's not in what you see.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's on the level of sense bases, the level of that background, the context, stuff you cannot directly attend to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Also implied in the word guarding.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not an active changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_06]: Guarding does not mean tackling down every single one.
[SPEAKER_06]: No, it just means protect the doorway.
[SPEAKER_06]: All you need to do is make sure the handle is locked and door is barred.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's how you guard it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Not opening the door and then punching everybody that tries to come in.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, and again, virtue, guarding of the sense doors,
[SPEAKER_06]: leads to samādhi, if it's done rightly.
[SPEAKER_06]: Because, what else is guarding of my senses, other than established context, that now defines my values, or where will I let my eyes, ears, and other senses go?
[SPEAKER_06]: So, something seemingly so simple like, oh, recollecting the Buddha, the dhamma, the saṅgha, the virtue... Yeah, yeah, yeah, it's fine.
[SPEAKER_06]: That is the base for samādhi.
[SPEAKER_06]: For a lay person.
[SPEAKER_06]: And then, if, you know, if your precepts are upgraded, up to eight precepts and so on, it can, on its own, result in jhāna and thinking and pondering that's free from greed, aversion, delusion, if you spend days, months, who knows how long.
[SPEAKER_06]: Of cultivating these right moods that become imperturbable towards greed, aversion, and delusion, and distraction.
[SPEAKER_06]: Then, all you need to do is just... because, again, you did the work, you have cultivated it, the animal has traveled, the mind has gone in the right direction for a long time.
[SPEAKER_06]: Now, all you need to do is just stay there.
[SPEAKER_06]: Just stay in that secluded environment, be moderate in eating, and this context will be fueled by those right things.
[SPEAKER_06]: And same like with Brahmaviharas, the loving kind, same.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's the establishment of the context of friendliness, non-ill-will.
[SPEAKER_06]: But it's not a technique that will result in this experience of it.
[SPEAKER_06]: No, it's something you have to frequently reflect upon.
[SPEAKER_06]: For yourself, for others, in every direction, up and down, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_06]: Until no part has been left
[SPEAKER_06]: Unreflected, to put it that way.
[SPEAKER_06]: And if you frequently think and ponder about it, the mind will incline towards friendliness, whether you want it or not.
[SPEAKER_06]: And the mind has been inclining and traveling in the direction of friendliness long enough, even meeting unfriendly people will not perturb you, or certainly not as much as before.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes, and that's completely different from
[SPEAKER_05]: When someone is... someone I meet is disagreeable, or is... And then I do metta.
[SPEAKER_06]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Counter it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Antidote.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Hatred means metta.
[SPEAKER_06]: Do it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Why?
[SPEAKER_06]: Not because you're really friendly.
[SPEAKER_06]: Just because you want to get rid of the discomfort of witnessing unfriendly persons.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, you're averse to what you're feeling.
[SPEAKER_06]: And back on to what I said.
[SPEAKER_06]: Most people's practice comes down to being averse towards their own states of mind.
[SPEAKER_06]: Trying to get rid of them.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, all you can do, when it arises, is just endure it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because anything you do,
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, all you can do is, yeah, like, endure it in a sense of don't act towards it.
[SPEAKER_06]: But, see, now we just define what you can do.
[SPEAKER_06]: Carry on evaluating, re-evaluating, thinking about Buddha, dhamma, saṅgha, virtue, friendliness.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can, you can, but it won't last, though.
[SPEAKER_06]: Because it's not directly dealing with what's bothering you.
[SPEAKER_06]: See, it already implies recognition that what I'm trying to get rid of is not actually the problem.
[SPEAKER_06]: The problem is the mind hasn't traveled far enough in the right direction.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, it can be a motivator to reflect.
[SPEAKER_06]: And even if you initially do it to get rid of it, again, the direction of getting rid of it is opposite of evaluating, re-evaluating, recollecting rightly.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, in other words, you won't be able to do it for those reasons much longer.
[SPEAKER_03]: If it's authentic.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, provided you already see that relationship between you and your own mind, which is what citta nimitta is.
[SPEAKER_06]: If you see it as a thing that's there, that inclines the here or there, depending on what you keep providing and allowing it to feed on.
[SPEAKER_00]: That should be the initial stage of trying to get rid of craving by craving.
[SPEAKER_06]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, yeah, there's craving involved, but see, now it's not actually fueling more craving.
[SPEAKER_06]: You're not acting out of that aversion.
[SPEAKER_06]: You're acting, okay, yeah, fine.
[SPEAKER_06]: I want to get rid of this.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, I want to abandon it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Do I abandon it by cultivating more ill-will towards it?
[SPEAKER_06]: No.
[SPEAKER_06]: I abandon it by making my context even less perturbable.
[SPEAKER_06]: Up until it becomes imperturbable and even more imperturbable.
[SPEAKER_06]: And there you go.
[SPEAKER_06]: You abandon it.
[SPEAKER_06]: The need to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_06]: The pressure.
[SPEAKER_06]: Being affected by it.
[SPEAKER_06]: And that's how you go beyond the hindrances as well.
[SPEAKER_06]: They're the symptoms of where your mind is.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, you go beyond them, by enduring them, and by cultivating the context that cannot be perturbed by those hindrances, and then, they cease to be... well, they cease to hinder you, as I said so many times.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, then, it's just agreeable, disagreeable, and everything else in between.
[SPEAKER_06]: But none of that can overpower, overwhelm, and limit your mind.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, that's often why samādhi, then, is referred to as boundless, unconstricted, nothing mystical about it.
[SPEAKER_06]: If your wholesome mood, on account of right recollection in the Buddha, Dhamma, Saṅgha, has been cultivated for years actively, on account of your virtue and sense restraint, there's going to be some pretty unshakable samādhi, pretty unconstrained.
[SPEAKER_06]: No worldly constraints can sort of limit it and bring it down, that mood.
[SPEAKER_06]: On account of that mood, you will be factually joyful, happy, with a calm body and content, because it's a good mood.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, you cannot take offense anymore, because taking involves sort of leaping out into that thing which is offending you.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're moving in the opposite direction.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: In other words, the
[SPEAKER_06]: The attempt to take it, if the Mahārāja presents it, is within the good mood.
[SPEAKER_06]: In other words, good mood can handle even the attempt to take it without fearing it, without trying to get rid of it or prevent it.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's included within it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it occurred to me that, from a mundane point of view, somebody might be sitting in an office, having to write a very difficult email, and they might say to their colleagues, I want to concentrate on writing this difficult email.
[SPEAKER_04]: But what they actually end up doing is closing the door to the office, so that they can be alone, and then they recollect the importance of sending this email properly, being aware of the consequences if they do it wrongly, but they might assume that this is
[SPEAKER_04]: Concentration, called like that, but what they actually do is much closer to what we have been discussing in samādhi, setting up a right context in order to do something properly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then they might go to a meditation retreat and learn how to concentrate, which is actually leading them away from what they were strangely already doing
[SPEAKER_04]: More closer to the actual samādhi, except they just call it concentration, and might not have understood that this is what they're practically doing.
[SPEAKER_06]: A hundred percent.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's exactly what it is.
[SPEAKER_06]: Because that's what I said before.
[SPEAKER_06]: Even when people are concentrating and watching their sensations, there is a certain context to that.
[SPEAKER_06]: You have certain motivation, intentions, why you are doing it so.
[SPEAKER_06]: But then you become unaware of it, because you're doubling down onto the concentration aspect.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, all you need to do is
[SPEAKER_06]: Again, become aware of the motivation behind your actions.
[SPEAKER_06]: My current action is concentration.
[SPEAKER_06]: Why?
[SPEAKER_06]: What is the theme, what is the context for me practicing this concentration technique that I find helpful?
[SPEAKER_06]: What is the theme?
[SPEAKER_06]: What is my motivation?
[SPEAKER_06]: Why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_06]: Because I want to get rid of the pain.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, that's the first step.
[SPEAKER_06]: How do you go about it?
[SPEAKER_06]: Where is the pain?
[SPEAKER_06]: Take that reflection further and you will stop concentrating and you will start practicing samādhi more rightly.
[SPEAKER_06]: Because when the Buddha described a skilled monk practicing samādhi towards liberation, you know, either walking up and down or sitting cross-legged,
[SPEAKER_06]: It wasn't through concentration.
[SPEAKER_06]: It was through constant reviewing on his mind about unwholesome states that are present, or could be present, wholesome states that are present, and could be present, and then encouraging one and discouraging other.
[SPEAKER_06]: Setting up directions, reflections, evaluations, so that his mind travels away from unwholesome, day in, day out.
[SPEAKER_06]: Purifying it, purifying it, purifying it, and then checking if it's pure, and then purifying, and then checking if it's pure.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's exactly where the work is.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, would you say, writing about the dharma can also be useful?
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, going back to one's writing, and then going back to it all?
[SPEAKER_06]: Depends, yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: I think, initially, if you write what you have acutely established as a context, yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: But if you start writing on its own, that will take too much of your concentration.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: It will become... it will require too much of attention, how you're going to become concentrated on that, and actually forget your situation here and now.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: And that same, like with the scholastic study, pretty much, almost always, results in that.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, in a sense, it can be useful to evoke the same theme if... Well, I found...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, for example, it might just be, maybe,
[SPEAKER_03]: Five sentences or something that I'll write to see if I've understood something.
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: No, that's a useful practice.
[SPEAKER_06]: We established that before.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then I'll come back to it the next day and see, oh, actually, isn't it could be much clearer.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then I'll come back to it and say, oh, yeah, and then I find in a week that it's turned into something
[SPEAKER_06]: Much clearer, yeah, because... No, that's... you wouldn't be doing any of that at the expense of your context.
[SPEAKER_06]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_06]: You're really just trying to to crystallize it further.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, it's then easier to sustain it and think about it in even further terms.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's not to impress some academic or... No, no.
[SPEAKER_06]: You're not writing it within the constraints of academic paper, with how it has to be written.
[SPEAKER_06]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's just conveying what you're thinking right there and then.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, it doesn't make sense.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, it doesn't make sense, exactly.
[SPEAKER_06]: It makes sense to me, but can I describe it?
[SPEAKER_06]: Can I put it in words?
[SPEAKER_06]: This context, this recollection, these values that I'm thinking about, that are sort of influencing my moods and so on, can I?
[SPEAKER_06]: Define that.
[SPEAKER_06]: Can I clarify it?
[SPEAKER_06]: And then, exactly, if you come back to it later, you realize, oh, there is more to it now that I haven't mentioned before.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or just that, oh, that wasn't that profound.
[SPEAKER_06]: Or, exactly, I was like, maybe it wasn't as good as you thought it was.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: When you try to put it in words, it doesn't really make sense.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's like, okay, well...
[SPEAKER_06]: Did it make sense in my mind or it just felt good?
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sometimes, you write something and because you're in a good mood, you're elated or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: You think it's so profound.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, you come back to it and you realize, yeah, that was just because I was in a pleasant...
[SPEAKER_06]: So, you don't wanna, like, again, good mood and so on.
[SPEAKER_06]: It will follow, but you don't want to put the emphasis on that.
[SPEAKER_06]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_06]: The emphasis is on that clarity, where the work of re-evaluating and recollecting is, and good mood will follow.
[SPEAKER_06]: And when the good mood goes away, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_06]: The thread of your understanding remains unchanged.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's imperturbable by the bad mood.
[SPEAKER_06]: And then, of course, eventually, the bad mood
[SPEAKER_06]: Will be a good mood.
[SPEAKER_06]: As the Buddha says, like you abandon the pain and suffering of a household life, you're abandoning by replacing it with pains and suffering of a renunciate life.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, the bad mood of an established mind, it's better than a good mood of a lay life and non-established mind.
[SPEAKER_06]: And you will know that.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, it's like, oh, yeah, it's just agreeable, disagreeable, as they would have said.
[SPEAKER_06]: You know, he would have teach somebody dhamma, they ignore him, they leave, says, oh, that's disagreeable to him, but that doesn't overwhelm his mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even the, yeah, generally the, yeah, like you said, the bad mood or the, sort of,
[SPEAKER_01]: Disagreeable feelings pertaining to the renunciate life are superior to even the good mood of the... Of the non-renunciate life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like there's that sutta, I think, it just reminded me.
[SPEAKER_01]: The blame or criticism from the wise is superior to the praise of fools and the... Oh, yeah, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, fundamental good mood is the mood when there is no emotion felt.
[SPEAKER_06]: As Sariputta said, the fact that nothing's felt, that's what's pleasant in a mind that's awakened.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, the pleasure of no mood means the pleasure of no possibility to be disturbed.
[SPEAKER_01]: It reminded me when you said about the... like, you used the word footprints of the mind, kind of the signs of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It kind of reminded me of a...
[SPEAKER_01]: That's sort of an analogy that had occurred to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just... or, yeah, similarly, in regard to the...
[SPEAKER_01]: Because people... you usually assume when you're about mindfulness of breathing, the kind of general idea is that it's very, you know, pleasant and calming and everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: But actually, it kind of occurred to me, it's not... it's not...
[SPEAKER_01]: I've often experienced it as being like being mindful of the breath.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not... it wasn't really pleasant or it isn't necessarily pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was kind of like... because the analogy that occurred to me, it's kind of like...
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeling or recognizing that there's a kind of a enemy stalking you, on your tail, waiting to kill you, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he's kind of always there, in the background, behind you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Footprint of his.
[SPEAKER_01]: He leaves his trail.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that was one of the things.
[SPEAKER_06]: I thought about yesterday, to mention today, but obviously kind of went in a different direction, was that actually, yeah, ānāpānasati, done rightly, most likely will not be pleasant first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's not going to be unpleasant in a sense of so painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_06]: But it's going to be like a like a certain dissonance, let's say like that.
[SPEAKER_06]: Like certain kind of at odds.
[SPEAKER_06]: And it's exactly that.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's that which is breathing.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's a perpetual misstep with what you think you are and your sense of control over it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Cultivate that misstep and you will abandon your sense of control and what you are.
[SPEAKER_06]: Obviously, if you have the right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you're not going to be able to see that murderer that's stalking you, so to speak, that danger over that body, without having that certain amount of composure, that knowledge and vision of the way things are.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, without having the right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't have it without that composure, you know, without that composure being to a certain level.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, you take on ānāpānasati.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like that simile of that bowl with water.
[SPEAKER_02]: Filled with water.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whichever way it tips, it just... Everything will go that way.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's like, you build up that composure.
[SPEAKER_02]: And now, I take on ānāpānasati.
[SPEAKER_02]: And what gets revealed is these things.
[SPEAKER_06]: These themes.
[SPEAKER_06]: And that which you build up is, yeah, it's the right view, the right composure, the right recollection, all of that.
[SPEAKER_06]: And then, when at least right view is established,
[SPEAKER_06]: Cultivating ānāpānasati is sort of revealing and fortifying that misstep, whereby you will cease to assume your side of the step first,
[SPEAKER_06]: And the breathing body is second, and start seeing the breathing body as the first, and you as second.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, breathing... doing ānāpānasati rightly, it's like a simultaneous undermining of your sense of control while you're breathing in, breathing out.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes, exactly.
[SPEAKER_06]: And that misstep, it's... it's that, like, subtle dissonance that's not pleasant.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: But, again, if you know the signs and features, you recognize, oh, it's that misstep that calms everything else down.
[SPEAKER_06]: Because all the disturbances don't come from things, don't come from body, don't come from breathing in or breathing in, breathing in out like this or in like that.
[SPEAKER_06]: They come from my gratuitous sense of ownership, gratuitous conceit, greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's where they come from.
[SPEAKER_06]: And misstep basically neutralizes them.
[SPEAKER_04]: You just cannot... they cannot fester and grow and live and persist in that environment.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, frequently practice ānāpānasati, the misstep of ānāpānasati, the misstep of unownable breathing, while you're breathing, and your sense of control will fade.
[SPEAKER_06]: It will wane away.
[SPEAKER_06]: It has to.
[SPEAKER_06]: Until there are no traces of it left.
[SPEAKER_06]: And the misstep is the... how things always were.
[SPEAKER_06]: Now, you're just not trying to pervert it through your assumption and negligence.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, which is then no longer seen as a misstep.
[SPEAKER_06]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_06]: Putting the first as second, the second as first, is defined by what you thought should be the first or second.
[SPEAKER_06]: On its own, it was always there, as first.